Guide to the William J. Benners Papers 1850-1940 (Bulk 1880-1920) MSS 28B MSS.028B
Fales Library and Special Collections
William J. Benners Papers
1850-1940 (Bulk 1880-1920)
Fales Library and Special Collections
MSS.028B
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
William J. Benners, (1863-1940), was a writer, publisher, and historian of dime novels, a class of popular fiction that flourished in the mid to late nineteenth century and into the early twentieth. The William J. Benners Papers consist of letters to Benners from family members, various authors, and publishers, fragments of dime novel manuscripts, several research and accounting notebooks, and miscellany such as scrapbooks and photos. The collection includes material on and belonging to Benners gathered by Ralph Adimari during Adimari's extensive research on the history of the dime novel. It also includes some personal papers of dime novel authors Charles Garvice and Emma A. B. Sharkey (pseud. Mrs. E. Burke Collins), and publisher Frank Tousey.
Provenance
The William J. Benners Papers were acquired by Edward G. Levy, the dime novel collector who made large donations of dime novels to Fales, from Ralph Adimari, editor and historian, in November 1964. Adimari had obtained Benners's letters and notes throughout the 1950s from Ralph F. Cummings, the Dime Novel Round-Up editor who nursed Benners at the end of his life. Levy also purchased parts of Benners's dime novel collection directly from Cummings. In 1970 Levy wrote to dime novel historian J. Edward Leithead: "As you may know, I wound up with most of William J. Benners's literary estate--about 2/3 of the items in my gift [to Fales] came from that source." Levy donated the Benners Papers to Fales in 1966.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
William James Benners, Jr. (1863-1940) was a writer, publisher, and historian of dime novels, a class of popular fiction that flourished in the mid- and late-nineteenth century and into the early twentieth century. Benners, also a poet, actor, and avid traveler, maintained correspondence with many dime novel authors, aimed to compile a directory of popular writers, bought and sold stories and publishing rights, and penned some dime novels of his own.
Benners was born in Philadelphia on September 27, 1863, the son of William, Sr. and Frances Ann. He had two brothers, Harry H. and A. Eugene, and a sister Novella. At an early age Benners showed an affinity for the literary arts, and was not much interested in working at his family's lumber business.
Benners was an avid reader of dime novels from age eight and read romances later in life. At ten he wrote his first poem, and at 25 he began writing some serials for George Munro's New York Fireside Companion and later for the Chicago Ledger. His professional writing career did not last long, but he was a devoted letter-writer for much of his life. It was when Benners was about thirty that he began his "vast letter correspondence with the popular writers of the day," according to Ralph Adimari in his biography of Benners in Dime Novel Round-Up. (Two copies of DNR Vol. 26, No. 9 are housed in Fales; one is part of the Ralph Adimari Papers.) The romance novelists Emma Burke Collins, Alex McVeigh Miller and Mary R. Estey were his most faithful correspondents. After his death a bulk of Benners's correspondence was destroyed by his nieces because of concern over their personal content. Ralph Cummings, the DNRU editor who nursed Benners in his last years and referred to the man as Uncle Billee, wrote to Adimari that Benners's nieces "didn't believe in his letters falling into other hands. They were putting stuff on the fire when I discovered what they were doing. I sure was lucky to get what I really did."
Benners planned to create a directory of dime novel and romance authors--a formidable task considering that so many writers published under pseudonyms, and different writers often used the same pseudonym--but this project never went beyond the research stage. He did, however, begin enterprising as a literary agent and a buyer and seller of stories and publishing rights. Adimari recounts that in 1902 Benners purchased the entire output of the Leslie Company, publisher of the juvenile magazines Frank Leslie's Boys and Girls Weekly, Frank Leslie's Young American, and Frank Leslie's Boys of America. Two months later he sold the Leslie material to William H. Gannett for $950. It is not known how much of that sum was profit, but we do know that Benners profited handsomely selling the stories of romance writer Charlotte M. Brame, who wrote under the pseudonym Bertha M. Clay. According to Adimari, who consulted Benners's accounting books, "he was paid from $15 for a short story up to $300 for a serial. So that sales may have reached higher than $10,000... When Ralph Cummings gave me part of the William J. Benners collection, at least one-third of the notes were devoted to Clay-Brame productions and in many letters to others he lauds her stories to the skies." Brame penned some 200 titles as Bertha Clay. Indeed, the Clay brand was so lucrative that several other authors went on to produce hundreds of stories using this nom de plume, including Benners himself.
Adimari writes: "Although Benners had many sweethearts he never married." He was engaged to Laura Jean Libby, a romance writer, from 1891-1893 but they were not wed. In a 1958 letter to Adimari from Ralph Cummings, Cummings writes that, "according to what Uncle Billee [Benners] told me, was that Laura Jean Libby wanted his $3 or $5000.00 ring to wear, and he wouldn't let her have it, so that was the end of there [sic] romance, so he told me, as he has been going with her for quite some time." After a long illness, Benners died on April 4, 1940 in his native Philadelphia.
References:
Adimari, Ralph. "William J. Benners: The First Historian of the Dime Novel." Dime Novel Round-up, Vol. 26, No. 9, September 15, 1958.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of personal correspondence from Benners's family and many dime novel authors, business correspondence from publishers, manuscript fragments, financial records and cancelled checks, notebooks, scrapbooks, and photographs.
Arrangement
Series IA consists of correspondence grouped into folders for each correspondent. The folders are arranged alphabetically by the correspondent's last name; within each folder the letters are arranged chronologically.
Series IB consists of undated galleys and manuscript fragments arranged alphabetically by the author's last name.
Series IC consists of miscellaneous items including cancelled checks, notes and photos relating to Benners's friend, writer Charles Garvice, several undated notebooks, including many that had been reused and annotated by Ralph Adimari, a birthday album for Emma Tell, a personal scrapbook, and a bound collection of serials.
Missing Title
Series IA: Correspondence, 1869-1940
Series IB: Galleys and Manuscripts
Series IC: Notebooks and Miscellany
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
Levy Dime Novel Collection
Ralph Adimari Papers
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Scrapbooks.; Adventure stories, American.; Notebooks.; American fiction -- 19th century; Personal papers.; Commercial correspondence.; Popular literature |z United States.; Personal correspondence.; Dime novels.; Victoriana.; Photographs; Legal correspondence.; American fiction -- 20th century; Galley proofs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts for publication.; Adimari, Ralph; Benners, William J. (William James), 1863-1940; Tell, Emma; Street and Smith Publications; Libby, Laura Jean; Leslie, Frank, 1821-1880; Munro, George, 1825-1896; Miller, Alex. McVeigh, Mrs.; Gannett, William Howard, 1854-1948; Frank Leslie's Publishing House; George Munro (Firm); Garvice, Charles, d. 1920; Collins, E. Burke (Emma Burke); Brame, Charlotte M., 1836-1884; Estey, Mary R.; Cummings, Ralph F., 1898-
- Series I A: Correspondence, 1869-1940.
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence to Benners from publishers and individuals.
  - The American Boy [William C. Sprague], 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baer, Lucy A.; [aka "Kate Hill", "K.F. Hill"], 1914-1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Benners, Alfred E. [brother], 1890-1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Benners, Mrs. F [mother], 1894-1902 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Benners, Novella [sister], 1902-1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Benners, William J. Sr. [father], 1884-1892 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bennett, Emerson, 1899-1901 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Carrigan, Franklin P., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Collins, E. Burke, 1893-1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Collins, E. Burke, 1895-1898 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    General note
    Various publishers to E. Burke Collins.
  - Comfort, Lucy Randall, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Corey, Frank A., 1896-1928 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Crowell, Mary R., 1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Currier Publishing [George H. Currier], 1907 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Digman's Magazine [E.J. Wood], 1907 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dumont, Frank, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Estey, Mary R. [aka Clara Percy], 1914-1919 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gannett, W.H. [Comfort Magazine], 1902-1909 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hanshaw, Thomas W., 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Heustis, Charles H., 1911 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Holmes, Mary Jane, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Homefolks Publishing, 1884-1892 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hubbard, Alice, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Jacobs, George W., 1901-1907 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Jones, Emma Garrison, 1891-1917 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - The Ladies' Favorite Magazine [J. Hodgkinson], 1907 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ladies' Home Journal, 1894-1902 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lupton, F.M. [People's Home Journal; Good Literature], 1892-1910 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - McIntyre, John T., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - McKendry, Caroline E. [pseud: M.J. Calder], 1869-1886 (Box 1, Folder 30A)
    To Mrs. C.E.M. from Frank Leslie's publishing.
  - McKendry, Caroline E. [pseud: M.J. Calder], 1850-1916, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30B)
    From various others; to Benners from C.E.M.'s niece.
  - Miller, Alice M. [pseud: Sister Mittie], 1890, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    1890 letter to Benners includes story outline. 1902 letter has Adimari notation.
  - Munro Publishing, 1889-1921, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - New York Ledger, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Saturday Evening Post, 1890-1919 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sawyer, Eugene T., 1922 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sheldon, Mrs. Georgie [pseud: Mrs. S.E. Downe], 1892-1920 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Stanley, Charlotte M., 1892 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Stoddard, William O., 1902 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Street & Smith, 1869-1899 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Street & Smith, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Street & Smith, 1904-1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Street & Smith [to C.E. McKendry], 1870-1885 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Stuart, Marguerite B. [pseud: Mary Stuart Broadbent], 1919 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Taylor, Annie J.D. [pseud: Leslie], 1910 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Vickery & Hill, 1895-1907 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Waggaman, Mary T., 1916-1919 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Walsh, Maurice C., 1916-1919 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - White, Matthew Jr., 1902-1914 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Wight, Emma H., 1914-1919 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1881-1899 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, 1900-1910 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1911-1920 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous, 1921-1940 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21A)
  - Business and legal correspondence, 1901, 1907, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 21B)
    1907 legal document has Adimari notation.
- Series I B: Galleys and manuscripts.
  This series contains galleys and partial manuscripts for various dime novels.
  - Galleys and biographical sketch, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Galleys for Mary E. Bryan's A Modern Heathen, with notes by Benners; letter to Benners from publisher George Munro's Sons; biographical sketch of Bryan taken from the New York Ledger (with an Adimari notation).
  - Manuscript fragment, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    One page of MS for The Haunted Bayou by E. Burke Collins.
  - Manuscript fragment, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Partial MS of an untitled piece by unknown author, with Adimari notation ("This may be E. Burke Collins?... Mrs. Miller?").
  - Manuscript fragment, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    First page of MS for Willful Goldie's Love Dream by Daisy Darling.
- Series I C: Notebooks and Miscellany.
  Series IC contains several of Benners's notebooks, many of which were later annotated and reused by Ralph Adimari. Other ephemera (photos, scrapbooks, etc.) relating to Benners is also included.
  - Legal Agreement [Frank Leslie Publishing House], 1902 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript: Benners biography, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    MS for a biographical sketch of Benners by E. Burke Collins.
  - Cancelled checks, 1894-1916 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Cancelled checks, signed by Benners, issued by the Philadelphia Trust, Safe Deposit and Insurance Company.
  - Garvice, Charles, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Notes, photos, and ads relating to British dime-novel author and friend of Benners, Charles Garvice.
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5A)
    List of serials and prices.
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5B)
    List of titles, miscellaneous notes.
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Small memo book with Adimari's written label on first page: "Titles and Names up to 1929."
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Benners's notebook with extensive notes by Adimari. Contents include: list of titles by publisher (Adimari); list of authors; one-page biography of Laura Jean Libby by Benners.
  - Emma Tell birthday album, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    An album of handwritten poems dedicated to Emma Tell.
  - Personal scrapbook, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Benners's personal scrapbook of clippings.
  - Book of stories, 1896-1916 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    A bound volume of stories culled from various serials. Includes pieces from The Strand Magazine and Detective Story Magazine.
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    A book of bibliographical notes by Benners, later annotated and reused by Adimari.
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Benners's notebook labeled "Expense Account", later used extensively by Adimari.